<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Autokatakritoi, or, The Jesuits condemned by their own witness being an account of the Jesuits principles in the matter of equivocation, the Popes power to depose princes, the king-killing doctrine : out of a book entituled An account of the Jesuits life and doctrine, by M.G. (a Jesuit), printed in the year 1661 and found in possession of one of the five Jesuits executed on the 20th of June last past : together with some animadversions on those passages, shewing, that by the account there given of their doctrine in the three points above-mentioned, those Jesuits lately executed, were, in probability, guilty of the treasons for which they suffered, and died equivocating.</title>
            <author>M. G. (Martin Grene), 1616-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13202</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12846734</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12846734</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41989)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 713:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Autokatakritoi, or, The Jesuits condemned by their own witness being an account of the Jesuits principles in the matter of equivocation, the Popes power to depose princes, the king-killing doctrine : out of a book entituled An account of the Jesuits life and doctrine, by M.G. (a Jesuit), printed in the year 1661 and found in possession of one of the five Jesuits executed on the 20th of June last past : together with some animadversions on those passages, shewing, that by the account there given of their doctrine in the three points above-mentioned, those Jesuits lately executed, were, in probability, guilty of the treasons for which they suffered, and died equivocating.</title>
                  <author>M. G. (Martin Grene), 1616-1667.</author>
                  <author>M. G. (Martin Grene), 1616-1667. Account of the Jesuites life and doctrine.</author>
                  <author>Hopkins, William, 1647-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Charles Harper ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [6].</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: prelim. p. [6].</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>"Some animadversions" is attributed to William Hopkins.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94454:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΑΥΤΟΚΑΤΑΚΡΙΤΟΙ.</p>
            <p>OR, THE Jeſuits condemned by their own Witneſs. Being an Account of the <hi>Jeſuits Principles,</hi> In the matter of EQUIVOCATION, THE POPES POWER TO DEPOSE PRINCES, THE KING-KILLING DOCTRINE.</p>
            <p>Out of a Book Entituled AN ACCOUNT OF THE Jeſuits Life and Doctrine. By <hi>M.G.</hi> [a Jeſuit] Printed in the Year 1661. And found in poſſeſſion of one of the five Jeſuits Executed on the 20th of <hi>June</hi> laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>Together, with Some Animadverſions on thoſe paſſages, ſhewing, that by the Account there given of their Doctrine in the three points above-mentioned, thoſe Jeſuits lately Executed, were, in probability, guilty of the Treaſons for which they ſuffered, and died Equivocating.</p>
            <q>Impudentiſſimum eſt Jeſuitas, tantarum veritatum lucem contumelioſam ſibi dicere, quaſi aliâ ratione fama eorum ſalva eſſe non poſſit, niſi omnes homines caecos faciant, &amp; vel mente vel memoria ſpolient.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Harper,</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCLXXIX.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94454:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:94454:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE the Sophiſtry of the five Jeſuits lately executed, in their dying Speeches, hath been already over and over convincingly diſcovered to the World by abler hands; and thus the main end of theſe Papers, which was to diſabuſe the credulity of honeſt well meaning people, is obtained. I take my ſelf obliged to ſatisfie the Reader, that it is not without reaſon that I have proceeded to make them publick.</p>
            <p>I had made conſiderable progreſs in, and almoſt finiſhed theſe remarks, before the * two laſt and moſt ſatisfactory pieces on this Subject came to my ſight.<note place="margin">Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the laſt Speeches of the Jeſuits, &amp;c. Impartial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations on the Speeches of the five Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, &amp;c.</note> I had no deſire to increaſe the ſwarm of Pamphlets, which the preſent licentious freedom of the Preſs ſends abroad; and therefore upon reading the <hi>Impartial Conſiderations,</hi> &amp;c. I reſolved to ſuppreſs theſe Papers, but heartily wiſhed I had been acquainted with the <hi>Learned Author of thoſe Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and with his intention to publiſh them, that I might have imparted my purpoſe to him, who would have improved this Evidence to better advantage than I have done, or can do.</p>
            <p>Having thus utterly laid aſide all thoughts of Printing, or indeed of finiſhing what I had gone on ſo far with, I was preſſed by a worthy Friend not to deſiſt, for that theſe Papers would not be wholly unneceſſary or unſerviceable, in regard my <hi>Medium</hi> was altogether new, and untouched by all former Animadverters; and it affords an Argument againſt the <hi>Engliſh Jeſuits</hi> in general, and Mr. <hi>Gawen and his Fellow-ſufferers</hi> in particular, which concludes, with great probability, that they were guilty of the Treaſons ſworn againſt them, notwithſtanding their obſtinate denial, and earneſt proteſtations of their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence at their Execution, might and did die prevaricating.</p>
            <p>There is extant in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> a little Book, Intituled, <hi>An Account of the Jeſuits Life and Doctrine, by</hi> M. G. <hi>Printed in the Year 1661.</hi> Who ever was the Author, no doubt it was written by order, and he had the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and direction of the whole body of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Jeſuits. The deſign of the Book was to vindicate the Jeſuits from ſuch hard thoughts of them as both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and the more moderate Roman Catholicks had not undeſervedly entertained; and to repreſent them ſo excellent and uſeful to Human Society, ſo innocent and ſo little dangerous, either for their principles or practices to Government, that they might ſtand fair for an equal ſhare with other Roman-Catholicks in the favour and clemency of his Majeſty, who retained a kind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe good ſervices had been done to his Father and himſelf by ſome of that Religion in the late Civil Wars. Thus much may be fairly collected from the Preface, where he brags, that <q>many of the Society were in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Camp, where ſome loſt their Lives, others being taken endured Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and other hardſhip. That there is ſcarce one Jeſuit in <hi>England</hi> who cannot reckon ſome of his neareſt Relations that died for his Majeſty, and that all that depended on the Jeſuits ſided with his Majeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now in order to begetting in other Roman-Catholicks, as alſo in his Majeſty and the Government, the deſired good opinion of the Jeſuits: It muſt be our
<pb facs="tcp:94454:3"/>Authors firſt buſineſs to repreſent to the beſt advantage the great Piety of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Loyola</hi> their founder, the excellent deſign he had in founding their Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, together with the admirable Rules and Orders of the Society, to ſhew the bleſſed fruits of the Inſtitution, and what advantages, both Temporal and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, mankind reaps from the Labours of the Jeſuits for their good, which our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor performs with a great deal of Art in the firſt three Chapters of this Book.</p>
            <p>The remaining part of his task was to evade with as much dexterity thoſe bloody Objections that are made againſt the Jeſuits Practices and Principles, for which they are decried, not only by Proteſtants, but alſo by all ſober Papiſts. He muſt ſo blanch over both their black and their crimſon Actions and Doctrines, that they may appear never to have offended either in deed or word, but as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> of thoſe horrid crimes wherewith all the world charges them, <hi>as is the Child unborn.</hi> And really herein, in the remaining four Chapters, he acquits himſelf bravely, and like a Jeſuit, and hath approved himſelf an Artiſt in fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and uſing Equivocations, and may be turned looſe to all the World.</p>
            <p>In this brief account of their Life and Doctrine, you find the ſum of whatever can be ſaid either in honour or defence of the Society. And their Emiſſaries may furniſh themſelves here with tools to rivet the affections of their Votaries and admirers; and to take off the prejudices of ſuch others as are offended at them.</p>
            <p>Among the five Jeſuits lately Executed, none plaid the Orator for himſelf, and the Society, like Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> who very handſomely ſummed up, in a few words, the moſt that could be ſaid for the vindication of both. And 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent he borrowed that part of his Speech which contains the Apology both for himſelf and them from our Author. It cannot be expected that ſo ſhort a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhould afford many Arguments to prove it, and yet I have four to offer for it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Whereas Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> cites <hi>King Henry the fourth of</hi> France, <hi>the Royal Grandfather of our preſent Gracious King, in a publick Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on — ſaying, he was ſatisfied with the Jeſuits Doctrine concerning Kings, as believing it conformable to what the beſt Doctors of the Church taught.</hi> It is obſervable, that our Author hath twice quoted the ſame paſſage in Anſwer to the third Objection, and hath cited no other paſſage out of the whole Speech. He cites it firſt with the very ſame flouriſh that Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> makes.<note place="margin">p. 106.</note>—<hi>I prove, by the Authority of</hi> Henry <hi>the great, our dear So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns Grandfather</hi> (much ſtreſs lies on that Relation) <hi>who—ſaid, I am certain, that in averring and defending the Popes Authority, they differ not from other Catholick Divines.</hi> And again, within four Pages, <hi>This is that which King</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth ſaid,<note place="margin">p. 110.</note> that he was ſure Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its taught nothing in this matter which did differ from other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks.</hi> It is one and the ſame paſſage, with that cited by Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> though he varies the Phraſe, and words it more pompouſly in honour of the Society.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Doth Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> deny that any Jeſuit ever taught the Doctrine of kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Kings, <hi>except Mariana the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Jeſuit?</hi> So did our Author before him, only Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> hath out-ſtript our Apologiſt, and ſpeaks without Book, in aſſerting,<note place="margin">That Mr. <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen</hi> learnt out of <hi>Philanax Anglicus,</hi> p. 94.</note> that <hi>Mariana defended it not abſolutely, but only proble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matically.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>all the Authors of the Society, EXCEPTING ONLY MARIANA—teach the contrary.</hi> And whereas Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> ſaith <hi>his Book was called in,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">p. 116.</note> 
                  <hi>and the opinion expunged,</hi> our Author tells us,<note place="margin">p. 115.</note> 
                  <hi>the Society would gladly have called it in, and that their General took order to have the place corrected.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> As Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> complains. <hi>Is it not a ſad thing, that for the raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ONE MAN—a whole Religious Order ſhould be ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced?</hi> So our Author complains of thoſe,<note place="margin">p. 116.</note> who <hi>will have it, that the fault
<pb facs="tcp:94454:3"/>of ANY ONE of the Society muſt, like Original Sin, infect all for ever, and unpardonably.</hi> Both you ſee take care that the Society may not ſuffer upon <hi>Mariana</hi>'s account.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> and our Apologiſts, agree in the uſe of a word very exotick and unuſual, Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> ſaith, <hi>I never did in my life MACHINE or contrive the Depoſition, or Death of the King.</hi> Our Author tells us,<note place="margin">p. 115.</note> that the Jeſuits are prohibited—<hi>adviſing that it is lawful to kill King or Princes, or MACHINE their Death.</hi> The word MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHINE is commonly, in the <hi>Engliſh Tongue,</hi> uſed as a <hi>Noun Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive,</hi> but I am perſwaded there cannot be many inſtances produced, beſide theſe two, of its being made a <hi>Verb.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And I think it not impertinent to add, that the Book whence I tranſcribed the following paſſages, was bought among other Books of one of the Jeſuits Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted with Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> and I am apt to believe not one of the five but had it.</p>
            <p>Now in regard Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> ſo far honoured this <hi>Account of the Jeſuits Life and Doctrine,</hi> as to borrow, what he ſaid in vindication of himſelf and his Order, thence, and one more, and probably all the reſt of his Fellow-Sufferes had it, there is little reaſon to doubt their approbation of it. And the nature of the thing it ſelf, being an Apology, requires, that the Account given of thoſe ſcandalous and horrid Doctrines held by the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, ſhould be as fair, cautious, and moderate as it could be contrived; nay, that it ſhould (as 'tis apparent it doth) mince the matter, and extenuate even the common and univer ſally received opinions of the Doctors of the Society. So that we have reaſon to believe, that Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> and his Brethren held the objected Points to the heighth of what this Author owns and allows, and did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce or diſclaim them no further than he hath done: We cannot ſuppoſe their Principles more moderate and innocent than they are here repreſented.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I thought it might be of uſe for the further ſatisfaction of ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt minds, as are apt over-eaſily to credit whatever any perſon takes on his death (meaſuring others by their own integrity, and never conſidering how much their conſciences may be debauched by bad Principles, and ſeared by ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practices) to repreſent the ſentiments of the Jeſuits in this Authors words, who is an Engliſh Jeſuit, and an Apologiſt for them, and one that ſeems to have been in good credit and eſteem with theſe very Perſons Executed <hi>June the 20th.</hi> That they may ſee how far one of the moſt ſober and moderate of them, even while writing on purpoſe to palliate their dangerous Principles, aſſerts the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Equivocation and Mental Reſervation, and the Poes power to Depoſe Princes, and withall how ſaintly and fallaciouſly he denies the King-killing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>The Principles of thoſe Executed, ſo far as we can learn them from their Speeches, are the very ſame; however they cannot be reaſonably ſuppoſed bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than our Authors. Now there being a moſt Helliſh Plot againſt our King and Religion, by Gods wonderful mercy, brought to light, and horrid Treaſons being expreſly and legally proved againſt them to the ſatisfaction of the Court and all impartial Auditors; when they underſtand rightly their Principles, theſe honeſt well-meaning Perſons, not only Proteſtants, but even moderate Roman Catholicks, will be more ready to credit the Kings Evidence, and be ſatisfied in the Juſtice of the Kingdom, which is now moſt impudently traduced. And they will further ſee cauſe to believe that in their confident proteſtations of their Innocence, theſe Jeſuits made uſe of Equivocations and Mental Reſervation, or that fine ſhift mentioned indeed by Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> but nót renounced by any of the reſt, <hi>material prolocution, i. e.</hi> To ſpeak the words materially, ſo as to utter the ſound of them without intending that any thing ſhould be ſignified by them. 'Tis apparent from the paſſages hereafter cited out of this <hi>Account of
<pb facs="tcp:94454:4"/>the Jeſuits Life and Doctrine,</hi> that the Jeſuitical Principles no way reſtrain men either from ſuch Treaſonable Practices, or from thoſe vile Arts of concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them.</p>
            <p>The paſſages cited are all in the <hi>VI.</hi> Chapter of this Account. In the cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I have uſed all poſſible Fidelity. I have tranſcribed them intire, and as they lie in order. I have omitted nothing but the ſecond Objection and its An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, as not pertinent to my deſign, though liable enough to Animadverſion, and ſome reproaches caſt upon other Roman Catholicks and Proteſtants, which ſerve no way for the Jeſuits vindication.</p>
            <p>I thought it was but neceſſary to add ſome ſtrictures by way of Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, on the paſſages I am forced to cite, for an Antidote againſt the poyſonous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which are contained in them. If I had not ſaid all that might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, I have purpoſely omitted many things, being unwilling, without ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to repeat what hath been already ſaid by others; and withall, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of this Author, is beſide the main end and deſign of making theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers publick, which is to make uſe of him as good evidence againſt the Jeſuits in general, and eſpecially againſt thoſe five laſt Executed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>An Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THESE Papers were ſent to the Preſs in the beginning of the Vacation, but the delays they met with thereby have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned their late and almoſt unſeaſonable appearance in Publick.</p>
            <p>You are directed to the Page of the <hi>Account of the Jeſuits Life and Doctrine,</hi> whence theſe paſſages are cited, by the Figure over againſt them in the Margin.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAGE 1. Line 13.</hi> in the Paragraph. <hi>l. 29.</hi> as Statera norum doth. <hi>p. 172. p. 2. l. 30.</hi> in his <hi>VIII, IX.</hi> and the following Epiſtles. <hi>l. 37.</hi> which are as good. <hi>l. 47. r.</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. <hi>p. 3. l. 4.</hi> declared her to be. <hi>p. 5. l. 42.</hi> not out of dread. <hi>l. 52.</hi> for which this account. <hi>p. 6. l. 42.</hi> Chaſtel. <hi>p. 7. l. 37.</hi> Loiola. <hi>p. 8. l. 23.</hi> for the honour of the renowned. <hi>l. 21. blot out,</hi> I paſſage. <hi>p. 9. l. 47.</hi> the Jeſuits then had. <hi>p. 11. l. 47.</hi> but they have politickly. <hi>p. 14. l. 7.</hi> their. <hi>p. 15. l. 18.</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Margin, p. 1. dele</hi> p. <hi>172. p. 3. l. 7.</hi> ubi ſupra, <hi>add</hi> ut. <hi>l. 36.</hi> He quotes Ofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, a violent Lutheran, charging the Calviniſts with a Doctrine they all renounce and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor. <hi>p. 8. l. 6. Lincolns</hi> Letter in <hi>8. p. 60.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94454:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Objections made againſt the Jeſuits Doctrine.<note place="margin">p. 100.</note>
            </head>
            <p>M. G. <hi>FROM theſe adverſaries, not of Learning, but of Truth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Objections againſt the Jeſuits Doctrine, which I intend to take notice of in this Chapter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Caſuiſt of the Society teacheth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tambourin</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits Morals, <hi>p.</hi> 345.</note> That one accuſed of a Crime which cannot be <hi>legally proved</hi> by the Accuſer, [<hi>i. e.</hi> not becauſe falſly Objected, but for want of corroborating evidence] may not only deny his crime, but alſo ſay his Accuſer lies and ſlanders him. Thus our Author treats the Objectors, and to be before-hand with them, gives his Reader an Antidote againſt all their Objections, by ſaying, they proceed from the Adverſaries of Truth, <hi>i. e.</hi> as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes them in paragraph juſt before, men who impugn the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Doctrine by railing, clamors, forging and falſifying their Books, who deſerve no Anſwer, but in the Ancient Catholick way of confuting obſtinate Hereticks, by Fire, and the hand of the Hangman.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>And their firſt Objection is, That the Jeſuits teach the Doctrine of Equivocation and Mental Reſervations, and therefore cannot be truſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Objection hath Truth in its antecedent, and Reaſon in its Conſequence, which is firm and undeniable. All who teach and practiſe thoſe Arts of deceiving, <hi>viz.</hi> Equivocation and Mental Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, are Perſons not to be truſted: <hi>Ergo,</hi> If the Jeſuits teach and practiſe ſuch Arts (which our Author denies not, but defends them) the Jeſuits are perſons not to be truſted.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>I anſwer, the Jeſuits teach nothing in this matter which is not the common Doctrine of all Schools and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> none excepted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How, none excepted! I know not what Artifice can bring him off without downright lying, for Proteſtant Schools and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities all expreſly condemn it.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>Nor do I ſee how it can be denied, unleſs we will ſay that it is lawful to lie, as</hi> Statera morum <hi>doth, for then we may infer as that Book doth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 101.</note> 
               <hi>That it is clear they are in an error, who ſcorning the name of a Lie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 172.</note> 
               <hi>make uſe of Equivocation. But that Author will not find any of his opinion, nor doth he leſſen but increaſe the difficulty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Author of <hi>Statera morum</hi> maintain the lawfulneſs of lying he doth ill. But I think he is much in the right, as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Equivocation, which is but another and a finer name for the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>The ſum therefore of the Doctrine concerning Equivocation is this: That it is always ill done to Lye, but not always ill to conceal the Truth by ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous Speech, that is, Equivocation and Mental Reſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is, in plain Engliſh, a ſimple, plain, old-faſhioned Lie, without either welt or guard is a ſin: but a curious, new-faſhion'd, artificial Lie, ſuch as our Author ſaith the Jeſuits, and all Catholick Doctors, hold lawful, and ſometimes neceſſary, is no ſin at all.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>when there is a juſt cauſe to conceal the Truth, then it is lawful (ſay the Divines) to uſe ambignous Speech; on the contrary, when there is not a juſt cauſe to conceal the Truth, then it is a ſin to equivocate. Now when
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94454:5"/>the cauſe to conceal the Truth is juſt, or not, dependeth on the particular cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of every occurrence, for which there is no rule can be ſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> One will find it a very hard matter to catch a Jeſuit without a juſt cauſe to Equivocate or uſe Mental Reſervation, if you conſult their Caſuiſts on the Queſtion, when there is juſt cauſe, and when not. But what need of a Caſuiſt to reſolve it? Our Author leaves every man to judg for himſelf, whether he have juſt cauſe or not; and then no doubt, both themſelves and all that depend on them, will find cauſes enough to juſtifie the uſe of ambiguous ſpeech when ever it may do them ſervice.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>This is the Doctrine of Equivocation, wherein the Society hath nothing particular but teaches that and only that, in which both Catholick and Proteſtant Doctors agree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Admirable Doctrine! 'Tis much the Society ſhould have nothing particular in it. If all Catholick Doctors agree with them herein, the more is their ſhame. But ſure our honeſt Country man, <hi>Joſeph Barns,</hi> a <hi>Benedictine Monk,</hi> who wrote a Book againſt Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was of another opinion: and one would be apt to think, that the <hi>Sorbon Doctors,</hi> who approved and commended <hi>Barus</hi> his Book, were ſo too. I am ſure he moſt unconſcionably ſlanders the Proteſtants in pretending their conſent.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>Among the Catholick Doctors that teach this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 102.</note> 
               <hi>are St.</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>S.</hi> Chryſoſtome, <hi>St.</hi> Ambroſe, <hi>St.</hi> Thomas, <hi>and after him a Torrent of School Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> He had very ill luck to ſtumble firſt upon St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> 'tis pity St. <hi>Jerome</hi> had not lain in that place.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Com. lib. 1. in Ep. ad Galat. cap. 2.</hi> Utilem verò ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulationem &amp; aſſamendam in tempore, Jehu regis Iſrael nos doceat exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum.</note> St. <hi>Jerome</hi> indeed ſpeaks ſomewhat favourably out of devotion to the Prince of Apoſtles, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that St. <hi>Peter was not in earneſt reproved by St.</hi> Paul, and in vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of it wrote an Epiſtle to St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> citing ſeven Authors for it; but St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath ſo bafflëd him in his VIII, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>X Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, that he made him weary of the Controverſie. It's true, about St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time, ſome Writers of good account, ſpoke too favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably of officious Lies. But St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. de Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dac. ad Conſent. Lib. contra men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacium: Enchir. ad Laurent. c <hi>22.</hi> Com. ad <hi>Pſal. 5.</hi> &amp; alibi paſſim.</note> condemns all Lies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, whether <hi>Pernicious, Officious, or Jocoſe,</hi> although he grant the two latter are not ſo damnable as the firſt. And that Father ſalves the beſt Arguments that could be urged in favour of Officious Lies, which as good as any, that Equivocation, or Mental Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will bear. Perhaps a paſſage in his Book <hi>Contra Mendacium,</hi> might encourage our Apologiſts Author (for he cites at ſecond hand) to abuſe that Father as a Patron of the Jeſuitical Doctrine,<note place="margin">Aug. contra Mendac. <hi>C. 10.</hi>
               </note> of conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truth by Equivocation and Mental reſervation; the paſſage is this, <hi>Non eſt mendacium cum SILENDO abſconditur VER<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M, ſed cum LOQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EN DO promitur FALS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi> But this paſſage makes directly againſt Mental Reſervations and condemns them as Lies, he ſaith, <hi>It is not a Lie, when TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH is concealed by SILENCE, but when FALSHOOD is vented by Speech.</hi> 'Tis evident that the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way of concealing Truth allowed by St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is ſilenced, and he eſteems it a Lie to ſpeak any thing that is falſe. Now in Mental Reſervation that which is uttered is abſolutely falſe, intended to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and in the judgment of the Jeſuits themſelves, would be a Lie but for the help of a ſecret reſerve in the Speakers breaſt, which can no way alter the real quality of the propoſition uttered.</p>
            <p>That this muſt be that Fathers meaning, will appear by the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he had ſo to determine in that point; the <hi>Priſcillianiſts</hi> defended
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94454:5"/>Lying as the Jeſuits do Equivocation by the example of the Holy Patriarchs, particularly of <hi>Abraham</hi> in the caſe of his Wiſe.<note place="margin">Aliquid ergo veri tacuit, ron falſi aliq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id dixit, tac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it ux rem dixit ſarorem. <hi>Aug.</hi> uti ſapr.</note> St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> denies that <hi>Abraham</hi> Lied, he did not deny her to be his Wife, which had been a Lie, but declared to be his Siſter, which was true; he concealed the Truth, but ſpake Truth alſo.</p>
            <p>As he hath abuſed St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who held it not lawful to Lie upon any account, no not to ſave a Soul; ſo I am apt to believe he doth <hi>Aquinas,</hi> whom he calls St. <hi>Thomas.</hi> For I find<note n="*" place="margin">Sepulveda de ratione dicendi teſtim. <hi>cap. 17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sepulveda impugning</hi> the uſe of ambiguous Speech in giving evidence, ſaith that none of the ancient and eminent Divines allow it, and before telling whom he meant by thoſe ancient Divines, expreſly ſaith, ſuch was <hi>Themas Aquinas.</hi> How he hath uſed St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> I have not had opportunities to examine, I fear ill enough: he cites no place, nor ſo much as refers to any, and I believe quotes Fathers as he doth Proteſtants upon truſt, and from no very honeſt Authors.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>Among the Proteſtants are divers mentioned in the</hi> Proteſtants Apology, <hi>as</hi> P. Martyr, Zuinglius, Willet, Melancthon, Luther, Muſculus, Wieleff, <hi>and divers others cited at length, in the</hi> 7 Section <hi>of the</hi> 3 Tract, <hi>under the letter</hi> M. <hi>number</hi> 76. <hi>and in the</hi> 703 page <hi>of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</hi> An. Dom. 1608. <hi>Though of the Authors there cited, ſome will not uſe the name of Equivocation or Mental Reſervation, but call theſe doubtful Speeches Officious Lies, which notwithſtanding they ſay one is ſometimes bound to uſe: So</hi> Luther, <hi>there cited, ſaith of</hi> Rahab, <hi>and concludeth, that there is an Officious Lie by which men provide for the ſame and ſafety of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi> Igitur honeſtum ac pium mendacium eſt, ac potius officium cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis appellandum. <hi>And</hi> Oſiander <hi>there cited, ſaith of the</hi> Calviniſts, Hane maximan ſeu regulam habent Calviniſtae, licere pro gloriâ Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti mentiri. <hi>The</hi> Calviniſts <hi>have this for a ground or principle, that it is lawful to Lie for the glory of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I confeſs I was at firſt amazed to find there had been any ſuch <hi>Proteſtant Apology,</hi> taking it for granted (as our Author, whoſe honeſty appears anſwerable to thoſe principles he is maintaining, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires his Reader ſhould) that it was an Apology for the Proteſtant Religion, and written by ſome Proteſtant, but upon enquiry, I find that his worthy Author is Mr. <hi>Breerly,</hi> who hath written a Book inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Proteſtants Apology for the Roman Church;</hi> a Book fraught with many prevarications, one of which cited here by our Author, gave me enough of the Apologiſt, and he and our Author may go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for their veracity.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>Yet Catholicks generally do not allow of Lying, but (as many Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) of concealing the Truth by Equivocation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here he ſtily and maliciouſly inſinuates, that Proteſtants are more favourable in the point of the lawfulneſs of Officious Lies, which he calls <hi>doubtful Speeches,</hi> than the Jeſuits or other Popiſh Doctors ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally are: but the malice and falſhood of this inſinuation, will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily appear to any man who is able, and will take the pains to compare the Caſuiſts on both ſides.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>Now that this Doctrine may, and ſometimes muſt be allowed, exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples will make manifeſt. I will inſtance in one: When His Majeſty after</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter <hi>Fight was conſtrained to ſhelter himſelf in</hi> Boſcobel, <hi>There was, as we all know, very narrow ſearch made after him. Among the reſt, one of the</hi> Pendrils, <hi>(thoſe Loyal Subjects ever to be commended in all Hiſtory) was as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked where the King was; he anſwered, that he knew not, meaning that he knew not for to tell them: He thought he might and ought in that caſe conceal
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94454:6"/>the Truth: And all the Jeſuits in the World are of his opinion. He was bound there under pain of High-Treaſon to Equivocate. And thoſe that deny Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to be lawful, let them ſay what they would have done. Sure I am, that if they would not in that caſe have uſed Equivocation or Mental Reſervations, they muſt have been either Lyars or Traytors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here he triumphs in a cunning inſtance, and ſeemingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicible,<note place="margin">A. D. 1661.</note> which ſuited very well the time of Publiſhing his Book. The happieſt inſtance ſure that ever was thought on, which (beſides the fair opportunity it gives him to extol the Papiſts Loyalty) ſeems to prove Mental Reſervations not only <hi>lawful,</hi> but even <hi>meritorious.</hi> He would make us believe, that we owe the great bleſſing of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties preſervation after <hi>Worceſter</hi> Fight to a Mental Reſervation, and to that honeſt Jeſuit <hi>Pendrills</hi> Confeſſor, who taught him dextrouſly to uſe it. I am apt to believe <hi>Pendrills</hi> is a <hi>made caſe,</hi> and not a <hi>real fact.</hi> Be it how it will, I conceive a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> might have as laudably ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Majeſty by a Lie, as Mr. <hi>Pendrill</hi> did by a Mental Reſervation. I honour and commend his Loyal affection and zeal for his Majeſties preſervation as much as our Author, and thus far I concur with him and all the Jeſuits in the World, <hi>That in this caſe he ought to conceal the Truth,</hi> but that he ought to do it in that way, by ſuch a Mental Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation I utterly deny. If we may not Lie for God, neither may we for the King. And there is not a pin to chuſe between Equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Mental Reſervation, and a Lie.</p>
            <p>But ſince we will not admit Equivocations, or Mental Reſervation, what would we have done in <hi>Pendrils</hi> caſe? he ſays, we muſt have been either Lyars or Traytors, there is no avoiding it.</p>
            <p>By his leave, I am of opinion, that there is no neceſſity of either. I think I can fit him,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. de Mendac. ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentium. <hi>c. 13.</hi> Quanto ergo fortius, quanto excellentius di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nec pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, nec menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar? Fecit hoc Epiſcopus quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Tagaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis Eccleſiae Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus nomine, firmior volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> with a caſe very like this, out of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> which will make out what I have ſaid, and withall ſhew, how much that Father was a friend to Equivocation. He tells us, that <hi>Firmus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tagaſta</hi> in <hi>Africk,</hi> had received a man (belike ſome perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtian) and hid him: the Emperor ſent his Officers to ſearch for him, who demanding where he was, he anſwered, <hi>Nec mentiri ſe poſſe, nec hominem prodere, paſſuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> multa tormenta corporis (nondum enim erant Imperatores Chriſtiani) permanſit in ſententiâ,</hi> that is, he would be neither <hi>a Lyar nor a Traytor;</hi> and having endured much torturing (for Emperors were not as yet Chriſtians) he perſevered in that reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is a plain caſe, this good old Biſhop never dreamt what ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice a Mental Reſervation might have done him; and 'tis further e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that if St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (who ſo highly magnified his Heroick conſtancy) had approved this Doctrine of Equivocation, he would rather have pitied the poor Biſhops ſimplicity, than have commended his example to imitation. So that it appears, our Authors dilemma hath not ſo perilous and unavoidable horns as he imagins.</p>
            <p>To conclude, though the forementioned be an example of veracity <hi>in gradu heroico,</hi> and perhaps conſtancy would often fail good men in the ſame circumſtances, yet I am ſure that as ſtrict conſcience would not have permitted any man to betray his Majeſty, ſo neither would it have allowed him to make uſe of a Lie, either plain, or artificial for his Majeſties preſervation. In ſuch a ſtrait he muſt have put on a reſolution, to ſuffer any thing rather than be a <hi>Liar or a Traytor,</hi> and to have committed the keeping of himſelf and his Soveraign to the all-wiſe providence of a faithful Creator,<note place="margin">1 Pet. iv. 19.</note> who knew how to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the ſecurity of both, without the help of ſuch indirect means and unworthy ſhifts.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94454:6"/>
            <p>M. G. <hi>The Doctrine therefore of Equivocation teacheth only this, that when there is a juſt neceſſity of concealing the Truth, then you may Equivocate; but when there is not a juſt reaſon to conceal the Truth, then it is a ſin to Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, becauſe ſuch Equivocation containeth fraud and double dealing, contrary to Chriſtian Charity, and that candor and ſincerity, which is neceſſary for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce among men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If our Author ſeem to have a more tender conſcience than his brethren, and will admit that it is ſometime a ſin to Equivocate; you muſt conſider, that he is an Apologiſt for the Society, and muſt very warily unfold this Myſtery of Jeſuitiſm: But if you pleaſe to conſult<note n="*" place="margin">Op. mor <hi>l. 3. c. 6.</hi> num. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sanchez,</hi> and ſome other leſs rigid Caſuiſts, you will find very ſlight cauſes may ſerve to juſtifie Equivocation, even ſport it ſelf, if a man do not ſwear to it.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>And in this the Jeſuits be no way ſingular, they teach but what all teach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Jeſuits are no way ſingular herein, or as he ſaith above,<note place="margin">p. 101.</note> herein the Society hath nothing particular, but all Roman Catholicks agree with them in this point, then they are even all to be truſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. But I will do our Author and the Society thus much right, they have above all other Writers obliged the World with theſe fine new Names for Officious Lies, unknown till <hi>Navarrus</hi> read Caſuiſtical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity to the <hi>Jeſuits Colledg at Rome;</hi> and further, by communicating the art of framing and uſing Equivocations and Mental Reſervations with the greateſt dexterity imaginable.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>The third and main objection againſt the Jeſuits Doctrine is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 105.</note> 
               <hi>that they maintain the Popes Authority in prejudice to Soveraignty, teaching that the Pope hath power to depoſe Kings. This is the objection with which the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits are every where cried down: And becauſe it is ſo much made of by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries of the Society,<note place="margin">p. 106.</note> I ſhall humbly intreat the Reader to give me leave to be a little more large in my Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Objection is very conſiderable, and ſuch as, after all his ſhuffling, he cannot get clear of: For what he ſaith doth not ſo much juſtifie the Jeſuits, as impeach all other Romaniſts of the ſame Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Tenant.</p>
            <p>M G. <hi>I ſay therefore as to matter of fact, for I mean not to meddle with the Queſtion otherwiſe, that the Jeſuits never did at any time teach in this matter otherwiſe than what was the common Doctrine of other Doctors in the Catholick Church, and for the preſent they are leſs chargeable with this Doctrine than any others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There needs no extraordinary meaſure of ſagacity to Divine why our Author balks the Queſtion, and will not meddle with it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than as matter of Fact. It is not of dread of Damnation for diſobedience to Father <hi>Mutius</hi> his precept: But the true reaſon is, becauſe he cannot meddle with it, without ſpoiling the deſign of his whole Book. He is an Apologiſt for the Jeſuits, and is obliged to give ſuch an account of their Doctrine as may repreſent their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples honeſt, and no way dangerous to the rights of Princes. Now ſhould he have undertaken the Queſtion, this deſign were utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated. All the world knows, our Author being a Jeſuit, one of the Popes <hi>Janizaries,</hi> he muſt maintain the Popes power to depoſe Kings, and determine the Queſtion in ſuch a way,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>England,</hi> and A. D. 1661.</note> as conſidering the time and place for this <hi>account of the Jeſuits Doctrine</hi> was calculated, would have proved of dangerous conſequence to the Society. But that the Society is never a jot the leſs chargeable with this Doctrine than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94454:7"/>Papiſts, notwithſtanding <hi>F. Mutius Vitelleſchi</hi>'s precept of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I will ſhew when I come to conſider it by and by.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>The firſt part of this Aſſertion I prove by Authority of</hi> Henry <hi>the Great, our dear Soveraigns Grandfather, who (when the Doctrine of the Popes depoſing Kings was objected againſt the Jeſuits, as an Argument why they ought to continue baniſhed out of</hi> France) <hi>ſaid to the Parliament theſe words,</hi> I am certain that in averring and defending the Popes Authority they differ not from other Catholick Divines. <hi>This the</hi> French <hi>Stories aver, this the Speech of that great King makes appear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">This Speech is Printed at the end of this Book. <hi>p.</hi> 137.</note> 
               <hi>this the Actions of the ſame King (if his words were not extant) would make plain to all the world: For how can it be imagined, that he who was in the account of all a very wiſe man, ſhould admit into his Kingdom men that held Treaſonable Doctrine?<note place="margin">p. 107.</note> How ſhould he poſſibly be ſuppoſed ſo forgetful of his own good, and the ſafety of his own poſterity, as that he ſhould plead for men charged to hold Doctrine prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to Monarchy, without examining whether their accuſations were true? No, no, he was not ſo weak as to become the Orator for his own ruin. He would never have made it his buſineſs to plead for the Jeſuits, and command their admiſſion; nay, further to take them into his familiar acquaintance, make them his Confeſſors, and build them Colledges, and bequeath his heart to them, if he had not been fully ſatisfied that their Doctrine contained nothing ſingular to the prejudice of Soveraignty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> He makes a great flouriſh with the Authority of <hi>King Henry the fourth of France,</hi> our dear Soveraign's Grandfather, in an Oration, which Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> in his Speech at Execution tells us, he pronounced himſelf (and he ſaith well, for few believe it was compoſed by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but by the Jeſuits for him) in defence of the Jeſuits. It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well known, that when the King made that Speech to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris,</hi> he came reſolved to gratifie the Pope (who had long, and with great earneſtneſs preſſed the revocation of Jeſuits from ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment) and not to take advice of that Aſſembly what was fit to be done. Had he admitted a fair debate of things, and ſuffered the weightier reaſons to preponderate, <hi>Harlay,</hi> one of the Preſidents of that Parliament gave reaſons unanſwerable againſt their revocation. But the truth of the matter was plainly thus;</p>
            <p>The ſame neceſſity of affairs, which at firſt enforced that great King to embrace the Romiſh Religion, now alſo conſtrained him to re-call the Jeſuits from baniſhment. While he was a Proteſtant he ſaw, there was no hope of ſitting quiet upon his throne, ſo long as the Leaguers (with whom the<note n="*" place="margin">Oratio Harlai ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud Thuanum, <hi>lib. 130.</hi> ad <hi>An. 1604.</hi>
               </note> Jeſuits unanimouſly ſided, and not ſo much as one ſingle man of the Society took part with the King) could have the pretence of Hereſie to excite his Subjects to Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. When he was turned Roman Catholick, one <hi>Chaſte,</hi> a Scholar of the Jeſuits, attempted to kill him, and confeſſing that he had learnt that Doctrine, which animated him to this attempt, among them, whom he had often heard, call the King Tyrant, ſaying, it was lawful to kill him, and that he was out of the pale of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and upon ſearching Father <hi>Guinart</hi>'s Chamber, having found ſeveral papers owned by himſelf to be his writing, which contained that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Doctrine; the Jeſuits were, at the Petition of the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>France,</hi> baniſhed the Kingdom, and <hi>Guinart</hi> was hanged. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their exile, he ſaw himſelf in continual danger of Aſſaſſination by their Friends: He was plied with earneſt ſollicitations from the Pope on their behalf,<note place="margin">Rivet. Jeſ. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulans. <hi>cap. 12. n. 5.</hi>
               </note> as may be ſeen in Cardinal <hi>d' Oſſat</hi>'s Letters, and at laſt ſaw he ſhould never make any intereſt in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94454:7"/>unleſs he would comply with the Pope in their Revocation. He therefore thought it good policy to make neceſſity a vertue, and try if by an unexampled piece of Clemency he might at once oblige the Pope, and appeaſe their reſtleſs malice. Hereupon he repeals the Sentence of their Baniſhment, receives them into more than ordinary favour, admits one of the Society for a Confeſſor, bequeaths his heart to them, and by all Arts endeavours firmly to oblige them to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, hoping he might find them as ſerviceable to him for the future as formerly they had been to the <hi>Spaniard</hi> againſt him. Otherwiſe 'tis notorious to all the World, that this great King retained too much kindneſs for his old Religion, to be Bigot enough for the Jeſuits: It was fear made him Court them, and after all the flouriſhes our Author makes, 'tis more than probable <hi>he was their Orator for his own Ruin.</hi> And when the Jeſuits found him not for their turn, they ſoon ſent him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Predeceſſor, having hopes of playing their Cards to better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage with a King in minority, and an <hi>Italian</hi> Queen Regent.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>I eaſily believe that thoſe who have already calumned the Society in this matter will endeavour ſome</hi> ſleeveleſs anſwer <hi>to this Authority of the words and actions of ſo great a King, but withal I confide, that his Majeſty will give more credit to the ſingle Aſſertion of his Grandfather,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 108.</note> 
               <hi>than to ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand detractions, and all wiſe men will joyn in his Majeſties opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">If ſo much ſtreſs lie on the Authority of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, why ſhould not the Authority of King <hi>James</hi> be as valid againſt the Jeſuits, as that of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th of <hi>France</hi> for them. But if you would underſtand truly the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th: See the inſtructions given to <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy</hi> his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador at <hi>Rome,</hi> where he paints them out in their proper Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</note> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This, or whatever elſe ſhall be offered, may be pre-judged and called a <hi>ſleeveleſs anſwer,</hi> but I am ſure 'tis as conſiderable as the Argument, which is an Authority of more pomp than ſtrength. And methinks the Jeſuits have little reaſon to triumph over the Proteſtants upon account of the Teſtimony of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, <hi>[That their Doctrine concerning the Popes Authority over Kings differs not from that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Catholick Divines]</hi> which if true, is <hi>really,</hi> though not <hi>intentionally,</hi> rather an accuſation of the Popiſh Religion in general, than any Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for the Jeſuits.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>But to go on and prove both firſt and ſecond part of what I aſſerted. Nothing elſe need be ſaid to make all my Aſſertion evidently clear, but only to give a true Hiſtorical account of what hath been done in this matter, which I will do ſincerely and faithfully. The opinion then of the Popes Authority in depoſing of Princes, was held by many Religous, and Clergy men, before any of the Society writ of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That other Orders, and that before <hi>Ignatius Loyala</hi> had foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Society of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> were Aſſertors of the Popes Authority in depoſing Kings I deny not. And I further acknowledg that the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its have not maintained the <hi>Hildebrandine</hi> Doctrine at that extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant rate as many of the Canoniſts have done: They have too much Learning, too much Wit, and I wiſh I might add Honeſty to boot, but I muſt not aſcribe too much to that. No, they have as much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for the cauſe as any Canoniſt of them all, but they are fallen into too knowing an Age to bear it. Their Order was Erected and Confirmed by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the III. A. D. 1540. at a time when Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was much retrieved, and when thoſe trifling proofs, would not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, nor would thoſe Arguments convince which had paſſed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, uncontrolled for four or five hundred years before.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>For example, there were ordinarily cited for this opinion, of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Order of the</hi> Benedictines, Gregory <hi>the</hi> VII. <hi>and other Abbots that joyned with him</hi> (<hi>as</hi> Deſiderius <hi>Abbot of</hi> Mont Caſſin, Anſelmus Lucen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis <hi>did</hi>) <hi>and</hi> Panormitanus, <hi>&amp;c. of the Order of St.</hi> Auguſtine, Aegidius Romanus, Auguſtinus Triumphus, <hi>&amp;c. of St.</hi> Dominicks <hi>Order,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94454:8"/>St.</hi> Thomas, <hi>St.</hi> Antoninus, Cajetan, <hi>&amp;c. of the</hi> Franciſcans, <hi>St.</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naventure, Joannes de Capiſtrano, Relagius Alvarius, Alexander Ales, <hi>&amp;c. of the</hi> Carmelites, Waldenſis <hi>and</hi> Bacon; <hi>of the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">That is, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. p 109.</note> 
               <hi>Clergy, very many Prieſts, and Biſhops and Cardinals, as</hi> Gerſon, <hi>Doctor of</hi> Paris, <hi>&amp;c. of the Lawyers,</hi> Bartolus <hi>and</hi> Baldus, <hi>&amp;c. theſe and many more were cuted in Schools for this Doctrine, which</hi> Barclay <hi>rightly calleth the common Doctrine of both Canoniſts and Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All this plainly diſcovers that the Popiſh Religion as Popiſh, is dangerous to the rights of Princes; all Orders, by reaſon of their immediate dependence on the Pope, are injurious to them, but yet more than any, or indeed all the reſt the Jeſuits. Purſuant to this Doctrine, there hath been for ſeveral years carried on an Helliſh Plot for the ſubverſion of our Government and Religion; and in order to the ruin of both, for the Aſſaſſination of His Sacred Majeſty. There were engaged in it, as hath been ſworn, of the renowned Order of the <hi>Benedictines; Corker, Howard,</hi> &amp;c. of St. <hi>Domincks</hi> Order, <hi>Kei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſh Dominick, Collins,</hi> &amp;c. of the <hi>Franciſcans, Armſtrong</hi> and <hi>Napper.</hi> of the <hi>Carmelites, Hanſon, Trevers,</hi> &amp;c. of the Clergy, many Prieſts, Biſhops and ſome Cardinals. But it was firſt hatched by the Jeſuits, and there are more of the Society accuſed than of all Orders beſides. But yet I muſt not forget, or omit, one paſſage I paſſage I remember I have read (in a <hi>French</hi> Book, Entituled, <hi>Traite de la Politique de France</hi>) for the Renowned Order of St. <hi>Benedict.</hi> In a Chapter, where, among other things, he preſcribes methods for the utter ruin of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, the Author adviſes, that a promiſe ſhould be made to the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> that they ſhould be re-eſtabliſhed in all their Ancient Poſſeſſions according to the <hi>Monaſticon,</hi> which, ſaith he, will make <hi>thoſe Monks move Heaven and Earth to bring all into confuſion.</hi> So that you ſee the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> of how good repute ſoever they have been, are none of the moſt quiet Spirits. As the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are the <hi>Popes Janizaries,</hi> ſo are the <hi>Benedictines</hi> his <hi>Spahi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M G. <hi>Though not withſtanding it is to be obſerved, that none of theſe, nor no Catholick Divine, ever gave the Pope an Arbitrary Power to depoſe at his leſt, as now ſome, though very falſly preſume; Their opinions were modified, ſo that their Books ſtood in eſteem, and were not thought to have deſerved ſo ill at Princes hands as now ſome would make them ſeem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the Paragraph before, he hath given them ſuch a wound, as the Plaiſter he lays upon it in this, will neither cover nor cure. It is well known,<note place="margin">See my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln.</hi> 8. pag. 60.</note> that very ſmall reaſons, have been thought by the Pope cauſe enough for the depoſing of Kings. And by accuſing all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Prindes of Hereſie, theſe Authors plainly give the Pope power to depoſe them <hi>at his liſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>All which I do not ſay to defend their opinions as good, but only a declaring matter of Fact. I ſay, theſe and many more were cited in Schools for this Doctrine, as a common opinion, before the Society was in the World: as beſide what I have ſaid, is manifeſtly proved, in the Oration which Cardinal</hi> Perron <hi>made to the third Eſtate in</hi> France.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Having made a fair Apology, to little purpoſe, for others, he now makes another with as little ſucceſs for himſelf, <hi>All which I do not ſay to defend their opinions as good.</hi> Well ſaid, but what then Sir? Dare you condemn theſe opinions? Do you any where ſo much as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate that they are bad? much leſs do you any where profeſs to diſown them as traiterous and falſe.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94454:8"/>
            <p>M. G. <hi>Whilſt then this was the opinion of the Schools,</hi> Bellarmine <hi>writ his Controverſies, and in the matter</hi> De ſummo Pontifice;<note place="margin">p. 110.</note> 
               <hi>he taught this Doctrine, and he took his Arguments, as be profeſſeth himſelf, out of</hi> Sanders <hi>a Secular Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It ſeems the common opinion of all their Divines and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts, with a Pope at the head of them, amounts to no more than a School point. He inſinuates, that though this Doctrine formerly was the opinion of the Schools, 'tis otherwiſe now. I ſhould be glad to hear that this point is at preſent determined otherwiſe than it was formerly wont in Popiſh Schools; But I doubt I may expect till I am a weary before I hear ſo good news: For ought appears to the contrary, our Author, and the reſt of the Society, are ſtill of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> opinion.</p>
            <p>But to ſerve the preſent deſign, an Apology muſt be made for <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and what is it? Why alas unhappy man! It was his ill luck to write in a time when this Doctrine was commonly received. And was it ſo? It had been worthy <hi>Bellarmines</hi> great Learning, to have rectified that vulgar error, to have diſabuſed the World, and anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Sanders</hi> his Arguments rather than to have urged them further, and confirmed ſo dangerous a Doctrine by his Authority. Thoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues for which <hi>Silveſter de Petra Sancta</hi> celebrates him, would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined him to this, but 'tis apparent the Genius and Intereſt of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety ſwaid him the contrary way.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>After</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>partly to vindicate him, and partly upon other accounts, four or five Jeſuits more writ on the ſame matter, alledging Authors who had writ before them, taking for the moſt part their reaſon out of former writers, that ſtood in Libraries, and were read without control in Schools: And this is that which</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth ſaid, That</hi> he was ſure Jeſuits taught nothing in this matter which did differ from the other Catholicks. <hi>But it was not enough for the Society to be as wary as others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If thoſe four of five Jeſuits have been miſ-led by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and former Writers, the Society ought to have cenſured both him and them, and ſhould have obliged thoſe Authors to recant. Till the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety ſet ſome publick brand upon them for this ſcandalous Doctrine, that its Authors may be no more in a capicity to miſ-lead others, the Society is juſtly charged with that Doctrine, and all thoſe ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences thereof, which it hath in its power ſo eaſily to redreſs.</p>
            <p>M.G. <hi>their Doctrine therefore after the death of</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth, their great Protector, was highly contradicted, eſpecially in</hi> France, <hi>and much noiſe there was. The Jeſuits them ſeeing that this Doctrine was</hi> Lapis offenſionis, <hi>and bred diſguſt becauſe they taught it, to take away all complaint of the Society, reſolved never to ſay more of that matter. So</hi> F. Claudius Aquaviva <hi>the fifth General of the Society made a Prohibition concerning this matter on the</hi> 5th <hi>of Jan.</hi> 1616.<note place="margin">p. 111.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Obſerve, I pray you, the reaſon of theſe Prohibitions which he thinks make the Society leſs chagerable with this Doctrine than others. It is no diſlike of it, but rather the contrary that occaſioned their ſilence. It ſeems the Jeſuits had (as they ſtill have) a very ill name, and Doctrine, that was ever a whit ſuſpicious, if taught by them was the worſe received for the teachers ſake. Now it grieved them to ſee this Darling Doctrine, and conſequently the Papal Power loſe ground, and themſelves hated and reviled for teaching it: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſtop thoſe mouths which were every where open againſt them, and becauſe the Doctrine was likely to be propagated with better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, by more acceptable perſons, they reſolved for the future to be ſilent in that point.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94454:9"/>
            <p>M. G. <hi>But becauſe that Prohibition ſeemed not efficacious enough to prevent all inconveniences, and give the World full ſatisfaction, Father</hi> Mutius Vate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſchi, <hi>the ſixth General of the Society, in the Year</hi> 1626. <hi>or the</hi> 13th <hi>of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, <hi>made a precept of obedience, by which all Jeſuits are obliged, upon pain of damnation, never to write, diſpute, teach or print any thing concerning that matter: The Precept is extant in an Epiſtle of Father</hi> Mutius, <hi>and from thence inſerted as a perpetual Precept into the eighth Congregation,</hi> in fine <hi>it runneth thus,</hi> Ordinamus in virtute Sanctae Obedientiae nequis in poſterum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriam de Poteſtate ſummi Pontificis ſuper Principes, eos deponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tractet aut libris editis, aut ſcriptis quibuſcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nec publicè diſputet aut doceat in Scholis, ut occaſiones omnis offenſionis &amp; que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relarum praecidantur. <hi>This is the Precept which hath now ſteed this</hi> 35 <hi>years, and never was infringed by any one; ſince the year</hi> 26 <hi>nothing hath been ſaid of this Queſtion in Schools or Sermons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 112.</note> 
               <hi>or public diſcourſes, nothing hath been Printed of it in the Society. This care the Society hath had to avoid all offenſive Queſtions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How little effect <hi>Aquaviva</hi>'s precept had, or how little it was regarded, may be plainly ſeen by the Publiſhing of <hi>Sanctarellus</hi> his Book, in the year 1625. and that approved by Father <hi>Mutius</hi> the ſelf ſame General of the Jeſuits, who Publiſhed the Precept of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 13th 1626. This Precept, upon pain of Damnation, was but neceſſary to a tone for approving <hi>Sanctarellus</hi>'s Book, and manifeſtly appears to have been intended meerly to prevent clamor, and maintain the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Society, more than the Authority of Princes. It provides but ſlenderly for ſecuring their rights; for though it prohibits wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Books, publick Diſputations, and Lectures on that Subject, yet it leaves them at liberty to inſtill that Doctrine in private, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they ſee it likely to find a favourable reception. Nay, for ought appears,<note place="margin">Libris editis out ſcriptis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſeun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nec publicè diſputet out doceat in Schuli.—</note> it may be ſtill vented in Sermons, (we have only our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors bare word that nothing hath been ſaid in Sermons for 35 years) for the Prohibition extends only to Writing publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſputations and Lectures in the Schools, if they forbear it in the Pulpit, their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence outgoes the precept. Since the publiſhing of this <hi>Account.</hi> we have reaſon to believe, (as we are informed upon Oath) that this Doctrine hath been preached by ſome Fathers of the Society in <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we obſerve the 0151 0146 V 2 conſideration upon which <hi>F. Mutius</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to prohibit the publiſhing of this Doctrine,<note place="margin">Ut occaſiones omnis offenſionis &amp; quirel exam praecidantar.</note> 
               <hi>viz. To take away all occaſions of offence and quarrel,</hi> we ſhall not find the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> much obliged to him for this precept. For firſt, hereby, if there ever ſhould be any of the Society ſo honeſt as to aſſert the rights of Princes againſt the Popes Uſurpations, they are prohibited doing it under pain of Damnation. And Secondly, there is no regard had to their Intereſts, but meerly to the credit of the Society.</p>
            <p>M. G.<note place="margin">p. 113.</note> 
               <hi>The fourth Objection againſt the Jeſuits Doctrine is that they teach the killing of Kings,<note place="margin">p. 114.</note> though under the name of Tyrants. So</hi> Mariana <hi>the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Jeſuit teacheth, and therefore had his books burnt at</hi> Paris.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This fourth Objection he propounds very blindly, and not in thoſe terms we make it. That we charge them with is plainly this. <hi>That they hold that Princes excommunicated by the Pope may be depoſed and murthered by their Subjects.</hi> This we put them to renounce in the <hi>Oath of Allegiance.</hi> And upon Trial we find more Patrons of the King-kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Doctrine than a ſingle <hi>Mariana</hi> whom they ſo freely give up.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>I anſwer that</hi> Mariana <hi>did in the year</hi> 1599. <hi>print a book intituled</hi> de Rege &amp; Regis inſtitutione, <hi>which he dedicated to</hi> Philip <hi>the ſecond
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94454:9"/>King of</hi> Spain; <hi>in this Book he did teach a Doctrine</hi> (<hi>after</hi> Dominicus Soto <hi>l.</hi> 5. de Juſtitia &amp; Jure <hi>qu.</hi> 2. <hi>Art.</hi> 3.) <hi>contrary to the Judgment of the Society, of killing, not Kings, but Tyrants; which Doctrine the Society con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and forbid, and the other Doctors of the Society all unanimouſly impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a great deal of craft in thus frankly giving up <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. As <hi>Bellarmine</hi> was excuſed before, he borrowed his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from <hi>Sanders,</hi> a Secular Prieſt, ſo here <hi>Mariana</hi> is not the firſt Author of this Doctrine, he learned it of <hi>Soto.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. It is repreſented as a ſmall ſlip, a ſingle Propoſition that is ſaulty.</item>
                  <item>3. They give him in compoſition for the whole Society, and pretend that all the other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Etors of the Society unanimouſly impugned it. Whereas beſides that it diſcovers the Authors paſſion for <hi>Mariana,</hi> it ſhews that 'tis not the King-killing Doctrine they diſavow, but have politickly picked out a ſingle Propoſition, that they may have ſomewhat to condemn for their credit: Whereas no leſs than two whole Chapters are hable to exception for that ſcandalous Doctrine. And the King-killing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in the terms we charge them with it, is as much the Doctrine of all Jeſuits who have written on that Subject, as 'tis <hi>Mariana</hi>'s.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>That you may know the truth, I muſt do as in the laſt Objection, that is, give you a Narrative of the paſſage. When then the General of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Claudius Aquaviva, <hi>underſtood that</hi> Mariana <hi>had put out an opinion of ſo dangerous conſequence, he writ to the Fathers of the Society in</hi> France, <hi>who had acquainted him with the whole matter, in theſe words, as Father</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>ſets them down in a Letter to the Queen Regent of</hi> France.<note place="margin">p. 115.</note> We have been very ſorry that no body perceived the fault until the Books were Printed, the which notwithſtanding we have preſently commanded to be corrected, and will uſe great care hereafter that ſuch things happen no more. <hi>This paſſed in the Year</hi> 1606. <hi>four years before the</hi> Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou <hi>condemned</hi> Mariana's <hi>Book, which was</hi> An Dom 1610. July <hi>the</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw Clandius Aquaviva</hi>'s Epiſtle to the Fathers of the Society in <hi>France</hi> is Apocryphal, it is extant no where ſave in Father <hi>Cotons</hi> letter to the Queen Regent, and he who conſulted an Aſtrologer teaching the Death of the King, and betrayed his Confeſſions to the <hi>Spamard,</hi> as Father <hi>Coton</hi> did, would not ſtick to ſorge a Letter from <hi>Clandius aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viva</hi> to the Fathers of the Society in <hi>France,</hi> at a time of need, as that was, when Father <hi>Coton</hi> wrote to the Queen Regent, after the Murther of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th by <hi>Ravilliack,</hi> who was ſaid to have been animated to commit that Parricide by reading <hi>Mariana.</hi> But admit <hi>Clandius Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viva</hi> did write ſuch an Epiſtle, and at the time pretended, is it credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (conſidering that ſtrict correſpondence the Provincials of all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der throughout the world keep with their General at <hi>Rome</hi>) that a Book which made ſo much noiſe, ſhould ſell off a whole Impreſſion, and be Re-printed twice, paſs ſeven years, and yet the General of the Order know nothing of that ſcandalous Doctrine it contains. But ſuppoſe him to know no more on't than the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent any ſingle Propoſition, ſo much in favour of Princes, againſt the Popes Uſurpations, ſhould not have eſcaped the cenſure of <hi>Claudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Aquaviva</hi> ſeven Months, nor yet ſeven Weeks.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>According to this the General of the Society did give order for corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting that place, and inppreſſed the Book, till it were corrected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That place, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though it were but a ſingle Propoſition that needed amendment, and yet I am confident a Copy of <hi>Mariana,</hi> with that Propoſition expnuged, would be a rarity few Scholars in <hi>Europe</hi> ever ſaw.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94454:10"/>
            <p>M. G. <hi>But ſome Copies being abroad (before the error was known to the General) which the Society would gladly have called in; the Heirs of one</hi> We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel <hi>a Proteſtant, or as ſome French Authors call him an Hugonot, Printed it again at their own charges. And this for no other reaſon, as it may be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but for lucre or malice to the Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Some Copies, thoſe were no fewer than two Impreſſions, the one Printed in <hi>Spain,</hi> the other at <hi>Mentz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoever offends the Proteſtants muſt ſuffer for it, <hi>Wechel</hi>'s Heirs <hi>Printed it again for lucre, or malice to the Society.</hi> Whoſe <hi>avarice or malice</hi> was it that procured the <hi>Moguntine</hi> Edition. <hi>A. D.</hi> 1605?? Was <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar Lippius</hi> an Hugonot? I have been informed from a good hand, That the <hi>Prackfort</hi> Edition was procured by a Jeſuit, who choſe <hi>we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chels</hi> Heirs, that he might at once publiſh this pretious Doctrine, and caſt the blame upon the Proteſtants when he had done.</p>
            <p>M. G. <hi>After this the General ſent a ſtrict Command to all of the Society (as appeareth</hi> Congreg. 8. tit. Cenſurae) <hi>under pain of Excommunication, inability, and divers other penalties, prohibiting all of the Society from writing, or teaching in private or in publick, or adviſing that it was lawful to kill Kings or Princes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 116.</note> 
               <hi>or MACHINE their death upon any pretence of Tyranny. And all the Authors of the Society (excepting ONLY MARIAN A) both before and ſince him, perpetually taught and teach the contrary; ſaying</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema <hi>to all that teach or practiſe any ſuch Doctrine condemned long ſince by the Council of</hi> Conſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is what the Society hath done to ſtop that Book, and root out the opinion, which I conceive will cleerly ſhew that this Doctrine is not reaſonably laid to the Society; nor could it be objected but by them, who will have it, that the fault of ANY ONE of the Society, muſt like Original ſin, infect all for ever, and</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">That Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin is an unpardonable infection is ſtrange Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, I thought the Jeſuits had not eſteemed Original ſin ſo great a matter.</note> 
               <hi>unpardonably, to whom I can give no other anſwer, but that I wiſh them more wit and leſs malice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How ineffectual this Command of their General hath been, and how true it is that all other Authors of the Society teach the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the King-killing Doctrine, which our Author, and Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> ſay, may appear by the writings of <hi>Suarez</hi> and others of the Society, who have, ſince the Year 1606, Publiſhed the ſame Doctrine with <hi>Mariana,</hi> though they have baulked that very Propoſition, That it is lawful for a <hi>private Perſon</hi> to kill a <hi>King,</hi> This Poſition they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn in <hi>Mariana,</hi> but how far they diſ-allow the King-killing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, our Author acquaints us, <hi>viz,</hi> as it is <hi>condemned by the Council of Conſtance,</hi> and no further. Now that Council hath condemned this Propoſition only. <hi>Quilibet Tyrannus poteſt &amp; debet licitè &amp; meritoriè oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidi per quemcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vaſallum ſuum vel ſubditum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caranza. edit. Duac. <hi>1659. pag. 630.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>etiam per clanculares inſidias &amp; ſubtiles blanditias vel adulationes, non obſtante quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praeſtito juramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſen conſaederatione facta cum eô NON EXPECTATA SENTENTIA J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICIS cujuſcunque.</hi> Any Tyrant may, and ought to be killed, lawfully and meritoriouſly, by any Vaſſal or Subject of his, even by Clandeſtine ſnares, or ſubtil Blandiſhments or Flatteries, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any Oath or League made to or with him NOT WAIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING FOR THE SENTENCE OR COMMAND OF ANY JUDG WHATSOEVER. How ſlender ſecurity doth this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree afford Proteſtant Princes, charged with HERESIE, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated and Depoſed by the Pope, and SENTENCED to death by the General, Provincial, and a whole Conſult of Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its? But there are many other fallacies couched in that Propoſition, and the Decree which condemns it, which are fully detected by my
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94454:10"/>Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> to whom I refer my Reader, That a Prince Excommunicate and Depoſed by the Pope,<note place="margin">In his Letter to a Perſon of Honour. 8. <hi>p.</hi> 163. That Princes excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate by the Pope may be Depoſed and murthered by their Subjects.</note> may be put to death by his Subjects, is a Doctrine none of the Jeſuits diſown; and if Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> would have cleared himſelf and the Society of this ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Doctrine, he would have more effectually done it, by renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it in the words of the Oath of Allegiance, and have averred, that all Authors of the Society teach the contrary. But this had been too bold a Lie; as I ſhall have occaſion in the cloſe of theſe Papers to ſhew, and therefore neither our Author, nor Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> hath any reaſon to charge us as guilty of meting them that hard meaſure, of condemning all Jeſuits for the raſhneſs of one.</p>
            <p>M. G. Our Author ſays, <hi>For my part,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 118.</note> 
               <hi>I do ſincerely make this prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation in the ſight of God; I do acknowledg his Majeſly,</hi> CHARLES <hi>the</hi> II. <hi>to be my lawful Soveraign, and Liege Lord: I believe that I am bound to reſpect, honour and obey hun, and that not only for fear, but alſo for conſcience ſake, as the Scriptures teach me. I do believe that whoſoever reſiſteth him, reſiſteth God, and whoſoever rebelleth againſt him, reballeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and procureth to himſelf Damnation. And accordingly, I do promiſe to be a true and faithful Subject to His Majeſty, and not only never to Act againſt Him, or Abet any that ſhall Act againſt Him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 119.</note> 
               <hi>but alſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and maintain, according to the beſt of my skill, His Life, Crown, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Prerogatives. And if I refuſe the Oath of Allegiance, as now it is couched, it is not becauſe I refuſe Allegiance, but becauſe I muſt not renounce my Faith to God. That to take that Oath, as now it lies, is to renounce the Catholick Faith, I am taught,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>and</hi> p. 120. He ſaith, <hi>If it may pleaſe His Sacred Majeſty, and the Honourable Houſes of Parliament, to make ſuch an Oath of Allegiance, as may, without trenching upon conſcience, contain all imaginable civil Duty in the ſtrongeſt expreſſions, that can be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I ſhall be exceeding glad, and moſt ready to take it my ſelf, and invite all others to take it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You ſee how fair profeſſions and promiſes he makes, I was tempted to believe he meant honeſtly. But this is only a ſmall ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Holy Water: After all, he refuſes to take the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and ſays, to take it, were to renounce his Faith to God. To what God I pray you Sir? I am ſure, to take the Oath of Allegiance implies nothing contrary to the Word of God, nor to any Article of the three Creeds. Sure enough you mean your Lord God the Pope, and your Faith given to him, which is inconſiſtent with fidelity to any Proteſtant Prince, or indeed any Prince whatſoever. It's plain for all your fair words, what you diſlike in the Oath of Allegiance. You have no mind to renounce the Popes uſurped power over Princes, to Excommunicate and Depoſe them, nor will you be brought to abjure the King killing Doctrine, for you promiſe and profeſs every thing elſe contained in that Oath, and your unwary acknowledgment that you are taught, that <hi>to take the Oath of Allegiance, as it now lies, is to renounce the Catholick Faith,</hi> ſtrongly implies, that thoſe Doctrines are in your eſteem matters of Faith. And give me leave to add, That His Majeſty, and the Parliament, have little reaſon to credit your promiſe, that you will take an Oath containing all imaginable Civil Duty in the ſtrongeſt expreſſions that can be conceived, ſince ſuch a Formulary contrived by Roman Catholicks, and profeſſing no more than Civil Duty, I mean the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Remonſtrance, met with ſo much oppoſition and perſecution from the Jeſuits,<note place="margin">See <hi>F. Walſh</hi> his Hiſtory of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance.</note> the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> and the <hi>Cardinal Protector,</hi> and is laſt come to juſt nothing.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94454:11"/>
            <p>IN theſe recited paſſages we have either an Account of, or an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for the Jeſuits Doctrine in the matter of <hi>Equivocation. The Popes power to Depoſe Princes, and the King-killing Doctrine.</hi> Whether our Author truly aſſert, that in theſe points the Jeſuits differ not from other Roman Catholicks, it concerns them more than us to enquire, and do themſelves right.</p>
            <p>Before I repreſent ther Doctrines, ſtripped of thoſe diſguiſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Author hath dreſſed them up, I ſhall deſire, and I think my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt not unreaſonable, that theſe four points be granted me.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That our Author is a Jeſuit, and a profeſſed Apologiſt for them, and accordingly hath given us the moſt plauſible and favourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Principles that could be contrived, ſo that the Jeſuits Executed, could not be more moderate and innocent, in theſe points, than the Society is here repreſented.</item>
               <item>2. That ſeeing Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> was the only man of the five that ſpake any thing in vindication of the Society, 'tis probable that in regard he was a very Eloquent man, and had a paſſionate moving way, he was appointed by his Superior to that ſervice, and that what he ſaid was the ſenſe of the Provincial and the other three.</item>
               <item>3. That M. <hi>Gawen</hi> borrowed what he ſaid in vindication of the Society,<note place="margin">See my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Preface.</note> out of this <hi>Account of the Jeſuits Life and Doctrine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. That Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> and his Brethren concurred with this Author in their Principles, as to the three points above-mentioned.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This premiſed, I ſhall prove that by the account here given,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Jeſuits, and indeed the Papiſts in general, do allow the Pope power to Depoſe Princes.</item>
               <item>2. That they prevaricate in denying that they hold the killing of Kings: For they deny not that Princes Depoſed by the Pope may be put to death by their Subjects.</item>
               <item>3. That the Jeſuits allow the concealing of Truth by Mental Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, when there is a juſt neceſſity, and that Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> and his fellow-ſufferers had, in the judgment of their own Caſuiſts, ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Equivocating at their Execution.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. That the Jeſuits, and indeed the Papiſts generally, allow the Pope a power to Depoſe Princes, according to our Author. He ſaith, <hi>That the Jeſuits never did—teach other than the common Doctrine of the other Doctors of the Catholick Church,</hi> p. 106. He cites Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the VII. and with him Divines, not only of the Secular Clergy, but of all Religious Orders, and Canoniſts for it, <hi>p.</hi> 108. That when <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> wrote his Controverſies, this was the Doctrine of the Schools. That <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his Book <hi>de ſummo Pontifice</hi> taught this Doctrine, that four or five Jeſuits more followed and defended him in it, <hi>p.</hi> 110. It never was condemned by the Society in any of thoſe Authors. And though two Generals of the Jeſuits ſucceſſively forbid the publiſhing of it, yet neither cenſured it as dangerous or erroneous, but did prohibit it meerly to avoid clamor and complaint. Our Author no where profeſſeth to diſlike this Doctrine, neither doth he ſo much as intimate that he is of any other opinion, than that commonly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Pope hath power to Depoſe Kings, <hi>though not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarily</hi> (as he ſaith to palliate the matter) <hi>and at his liſt,</hi> yet if they be Hereticks, or favourers of them, Schiſmaticks, diminiſhers of the Church Rights and Revenues, ſevere to Roman Catholicks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I preſume none will deny but that His Sacred Majeſty is, in the <hi>Judgment of the Roman Court,</hi> obnoxious to the Popes Cenſure upon all theſe accounts.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94454:11"/>
            <p n="11">11. In the matter of the King-killing Doctrine, this Author and Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> ſhuffle baſely, and baulk the point. The dangerous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine we charge them with is this, <hi>That Princes Excommunicate by the Pope may be Depoſed and Murthered by their Subjects.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Si ſub voce Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur depoſitio, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>atio quae p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Canonicam interdum ſit, ſic conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> propoſitionem, impan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i vel OCCIDI à QUIBUSCUDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUE poſſe, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer <hi>Suarez.</hi> Deſenſ. ſid. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. <hi>lib.</hi> &amp;. <hi>c. 6. §. 24.</hi> Suariz. ibid. <hi>cap. 4. §. 14.</hi> Eil. de ſum. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt, <hi>l. 5. c 8.</hi> Bican. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov. Anglic. Suarez ibid. <hi>§ 20. I abjure that Heretical and Traiterous Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>If the Sentence of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication contain a Depoſition and Abſolution of the Subjects from their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, which is ſometimes done by Canonical Sentence, then that Propoſition is true, that he,</hi> viz, <hi>[the Excommunicate Prince] may he Depoſed or killed by any whatſoever, without incurring any penalty,</hi> ſaith <hi>Suarez.</hi> And the ſame Author ſaith, <hi>That after Sentence paſſed upon him—he may be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a Tyrant, and killed by any private perſon.</hi> Both <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Becan</hi> prove the Popes power to Depoſe Kings, and to condemn them to death, by the Example of <hi>Jehoiada</hi> the High Prieſt, <hi>who firſt deprived Athalia of the Kingdom, and afterward of her Life.</hi> So that you ſee more than a ſingle <hi>Mariana,</hi> defend the King-killing Doctrine, which while they renounce and impugn unanimouſly, in that Propoſition condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> they as unanimouſly maintain, when the Pope interpoſes his fatal Sentence, and alters the Caſe. 'Tis plain the Jeſuits thenmſeves think that Decree of the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> affords no ſecurity to Princes againſt the Popes Sentence. What ſaith <hi>Suarez.</hi> to King <hi>James. where doth the King read in the Council of</hi> Conſtance <hi>ſuch a word, as a PRINCE EXCOMM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NICATED or DEPRIVED by the POPE?</hi> I have heard ſome Jeſuited Papiſts ſay (whether in ſincerity or not, God knows) that they would take the Oath of Allegiance, were the word HERETICAL abated them; they ſay the Civil Magiſtrate may declare what is <hi>Treaſon,</hi> but 'tis the Prerogative of the Church to declare what is <hi>Hereſie.</hi> Now whoſoever upon this ſcore objects againſt the Oath, muſt acknowledg that the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> hath not Condemned the King-killing Doctrine, nor do the Jeſuits ſay <hi>Anathema</hi> to it. For did the Decree extend to the condemnation of the Doctrine abjured in the Oath of Allegiance, they might abjure it as Heretical, being condemned by a General Council, but ſo long as they refuſe it on this account, 'tis evident they do not believe the Council ever intended to cenſure it, and certainly it never did.</p>
            <p>So that for ought that our Author or Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> hath ſaid, it is reaſonable ſtill to object theſe bloody Tenents to the Jeſuits, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to this day to have kept on foot that League for the extirpation of Heretical Princes, which <hi>F. Campian</hi> ſaith, all the Jeſuits in the World had entred into in his days near 100 years ago,<note place="margin">Campianus Ep. ad Conſidiarias Regi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae Argliae <hi>p. 22.</hi>
               </note> and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the many defeats Providence hath given them in their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes, yet they deſpair not of effecting it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> Seeing then the Jeſuits Principles even as repreſented moſt plauſibly by an Apologiſt of their own, are ſo dangerous and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to Princes, eſpecially ſuch as are of the Proteſtant Religion; and ſince we have ſo much reaſon to believe Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> and the reſt were of the ſame Principles, in the forementioned points with our Author, and there have been treaſonable practices agreeable to their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſo legally and fully proved upon them, as ſatisfied the Jury and Bench to Convict and Condemn them. I think that perſon wants both Faith and Charity, who will not believe them guilty: He lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle knows what a Jeſuit is, and is utterly unacquainted with the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Mental Reſervations, who ſuſpends his judgment, till one of them ſhall confeſs.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94454:12"/>
            <p n="3">III. Touching the matter of Equivocation, you ſee what our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors judgment is, he doth not meerly aſſert that it is lawful <hi>to conceal Truth by doubtful Speech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 100. &amp; p. 101.</note> 
               <hi>that is, Equivocation or Mental Reſervation,</hi> but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently pretends the conſent of all Ages and Parties, <hi>all Schools and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, none excepted,</hi> as though it were an uncontroverted point. Which, were it true, would make Equivocation and Mental Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Doctrine more truly Catholick than Tranſubſtantiation, or Invocation of Saints, which they deny not to be unanimouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Our Author ſaith, that when there is a <hi>juſt cauſe to conceal the Truth, then it is lawful (ſay the Divines) to uſe Ambiguous Speech,</hi> that is, <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation and Mental Reſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are now further to enquire what is a juſt cauſe to Equivocate, and ſee whether the Jeſuits lately Executed had ſuch cauſe as might, in the Judgment of their Caſuiſts, make it lawful for them to die thus concealing the Truth.</p>
            <p>Our Author plainly tells us.<note place="margin">p. 102.</note>—<hi>When the cauſe to conceal Truth is juſt, or not, depends on the particular circumſtance of every occurence for which no rule can be ſet.</hi> This, you will ſay, is pretty fair, he leaves every man to judg for himſelf, when he hath juſt cauſe to Equivocate, which a Jeſuit will never fail to have, as oft as this Art may do him ſervice.</p>
            <p>If you pleaſe to conſult other Caſuiſts of the Society<note n="*" place="margin">Quoties id neceſſarium aut utile eſt, ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute corporis, honorem, res fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliares tuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das. Op. mor. <hi>l. 3. c. 6. n. 19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sanchez</hi> will tell you. <hi>the defence of Life, Honour, or Goods, is a juſt cauſe.</hi> When a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. num. <hi>27.</hi> Sed qui praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puè aequivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione excolue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, eo video ſuiſſe Anglos. Ep. ad Fr. Duc. <hi>p. 108.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>asked by any Incompetent Judg.</hi> And 'tis notorious the Jeſuits deny any Lay-man to be the Competent Judg of Eccleſiaſticks; or if a Competent Judg <hi>ask a Queſtion extrajudicially.</hi> Here is ſcope enough.</p>
            <p>But perhaps it were more adviſable to conſult Jeſuits of our own Nation, for * <hi>Caſaubon</hi> obſerves, that <hi>they of all men have taken moſt pains in cultivating the Art of Equivocation.</hi> And I may add, have always practiſed it moſt licentiouſly.</p>
            <p>Now what hath <hi>F. Garnet</hi> given under his hand in this matter. <hi>As oft as there is occaſion, for neceſſary defence, for avoiding of ſome injury and damage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt the Traytors. ſheet <hi>u. fol.</hi> 4. <hi>Mitig.</hi> c. 7. n. 14.</note> 
               <hi>or for obtaining ſome good of moment, without the peril of any man, Equivocation is lawful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Father <hi>Parſons</hi> reſolves, that <hi>Equivocations muſt ſometimes be practiſed when no other evaſion can be found for defence of Innocency, Juſtice, SECRECY, or the like urgent occaſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now enquire whether the Jeſuits had not ſeveral of theſe cauſes to deny what was ſworn againſt them, and take it upon their death, that they were as <hi>innocent as the Child unborn.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The defence of their own <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> which would have been irreparably ruined, ſhould they either by an ingenuous Confeſſion, or but by ſilence have owned themſelves guilty.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Honor of the Society</hi> was at ſtake, which would have been ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt, ſhould a <hi>Provincial,</hi> a <hi>Procurator,</hi> and other principal Fathers have owned themſelves guilty of ſo Helliſh a Plot.</item>
               <item>3. To <hi>avoid thoſe ſeverities,</hi> which though in truth might juſtly have been inflicted on Roman Catholicks, yet the Jeſuits eſteem <hi>injuries</hi> as well as <hi>damages.</hi> Should the dormant Laws be throughly awakened, as 'tis no doubt but they would (ſhould theſe Jeſuits have made a free Confeſſion) the Popiſh Intereſt would loſe ground apace.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bzovius de Pontij.</hi> Rom. cap. 46. p. 621. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſcuſ.</hi> of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of <hi>W. B.</hi> p. 22, 23.</note>
               </item>
               <item>4. 'Tis a <hi>good of no ſmall moment</hi> to purchaſe themſelves the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Innocents and Martyrs, as in opinion of <hi>Bzovius</hi> and <hi>Parſons, Campian</hi> and <hi>Garnet</hi> were, and all that follow them in the ſame cauſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94454:12"/>are ſure to be reputed. And this will much advance the good of the Catholick Cauſe, which would be in danger of loſing many well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people, by their ſincere Confeſſion, who will be confirmed in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion, when they ſee theſe Jeſuits proteſt their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence with their dying breath.</item>
               <item>5. They had a mighty work upon their hands, <hi>no leſs than the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of three Kingdoms,</hi> and for ought they knew, the ſubduing <hi>of a Peſtilent Hereſie</hi> which hath domineered over a great part of this Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern World a long time, as Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> ſaid.<note place="margin">See his Letter to <hi>F. la Chaiſe.</hi>
                  </note> And the ſame work appears to be ſtill carrying on, and I am ſure requires ſecreſie, for 'tis a work of Darkneſs. Now I ſhall argue as our Author did. There being ſuch a deſign in hand, for the good of their Holy Mother the Church, and their moſt Holy Father the Pope, whoſe Intereſts are, no doubt, as dear to them, as ever was the preſervation of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and when theſe two ſtand in competition, as it ſeems at preſent they do, the former are much dearer. For to betray the Intereſts of the Church, or to procure its hurt (as a free confeſſion of guilt would have done) is not only Treaſon but Sacriledg. In this caſe 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bables the Jeſuits thought they might and ought conceal the Truth; and our Author, (if he were not one of them) and all the Jeſuits in the World are of opinion that they were bound under pain of the higheſt Treaſon and Sacriledg to boot, to equivocate. If they would not they muſt, by our Authors Logick, have been Lyars or Traitors. And ſuch, I fear, in both requeſts they died, for all the help of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Inference.</hi> Seeing then the Jeſuits Principles, as repreſented by our Author, allow Equivocations and Mental Reſervations in juſt neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and thoſe lately Executed had, in the opinion of their own Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, a juſt neceſſity of concealing Truth, upon ſuch evidence of their guilt, we have reaſon to believe, that in their proteſtations of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, at <hi>Tybourn,</hi> they acted ſuitably to their Principles, and died like Jeſuits as they had lived, prevaricating and jugling.</p>
            <p>There are two things, I obſerve, ſtick with ſome perſons, the one is, that Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> profeſſes that <hi>he doth not make uſe of any Equivocation; Mental Reſervation, or Material Prolocution.</hi> So the reſt.</p>
            <p>But for the ſatisfaction of ſuch perſons, I deſire them to conſider what Father <hi>Parſons</hi> teaches,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide citat. apud Abbot Antilog.</hi> fol. 13. <hi>Ita &amp; Sanchez Op. mor.</hi> l. 3. c. 6. nu. 45. See o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cited in the Animadv. on the Jeſuits laſt Speeches, <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>That if you be asked whether you do not Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, you may anſwer no, but with another Equivocation</hi> —and ſo, <hi>as often as you ſhall be askt this or the like Queſtion, you may deny that you did Equivocate with a freſh Equivocation,</hi> ſo that their renouncing all Equivocation, is no ſecurity of their ſincere dealing. And if it be replied, here was no ſuch neceſſity, they were not examined, but offer freely to ſpeak plainly, and without Equivocation, that varies not the caſe. For the Caſuiſts allow the uſe of Equivocations, <hi>Sive interrogatus ſive propria ſponte,</hi> whether a man anſwer a queſtion, or ſpeak of his own accord.<note place="margin">Si quis vel ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus vel cum ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is; ſive inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatus ſive propria ſponte—jaret ſe non feciſſe ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, <hi>&amp;c. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chez. op. mor. l. 3. c. 6. n. 16.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The other is, that they uſed ſuch dreadful Imprecations, and high Aſſeverations, and this at the point of Death, when perſons of the moſt proſtitute conſcience, are not without ſcruples and remorſe.</p>
            <p>But they who regard this objection, little conſider how far a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Notion the Jeſuits have of ſuch Ambiguous Speech, from what they have. They behold Equivocations as a ſort of Lies, and not too without ſin; but the Jeſuits look upon them as perfectly blameleſs, as ſometimes neceſſary and laudable, and ſo innocent, as that to uſe them was not inconſiſtent with our<note n="*" place="margin">Parſons <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tig.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> n. <hi>45.</hi> Sten. nu. <hi>58.</hi> nu. <hi>72.</hi>
               </note> Saviours perfection, who did no
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94454:13"/>ſin,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So</hi> Heiſſuis: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſut. Aphor. <hi>c. 4.</hi> Aph. <hi>4. nu. 130.</hi>
               </note> neither was there guile found in his mouth, and a remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt lying and perjuries. And if men have ſuch apprehenſions of Equivocating, I ſee no reaſon, why at their Death they ſhould in the leaſt ſcruple a practice ſo harmleſs and innocent, more than at any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time.<note place="margin">Gun-powder Treaſon. <hi>p.</hi> 219, 220, 221.</note> We ſee it hath been often practiſed. <hi>Treſham,</hi> one of the Gunpowder Traytors, confeſſed that <hi>Garnet</hi> was privy to the Treaſon, and had talked with him about it. After, upon his Death-bed, not above three hours before his Death, <hi>under his hand, and upon his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> he revoked what upon his Examination he had Confeſſed; and averred that he had not ſeen <hi>Garnet</hi> in ſixteen years before, this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation was afterwards proved falſe upon Oath, and <hi>Garnet</hi> himſelf acknowledged the contrary, and that he had often ſeen him within two years. Hereupon <hi>Garnet</hi> being asked what he thought of <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhams</hi> dying Proteſtation? anſwered, It might be he meant to Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate. Which ſhews, that in <hi>Garnets</hi> judgment, to Equivocate on ones Death-bed, and <hi>that upon his Salvation,</hi> as <hi>Treſham</hi> did, and as theſe Jeſuits proteſted their Innocence, is no ſuch horrid matter as to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants it appears. And I obſerve, in the Hiſtory of the Gun-powder Treaſon,<note place="margin">Gun-powder Treaſon. <hi>p.</hi> 227. I am ſorry that I did diſſemble with them; but I did not think they had ſuch proof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me. See the late Tryals and particularly Mr. <hi>Jenniſons</hi> Depoſition.</note> that as <hi>Garnet</hi> himſelf practiſed Equivocation, and that with ſo many deteſtable Execrations as wounded the hearts of the Lords of the Council to hear him, yet when he came to his Execution, though he asked thoſe Lords pardon for his diſſembling with them, deeming it an offence againſt good manners, yet begs no pardon of God for it, judging it no offence againſt him at all.</p>
            <p>As for the Jeſuits lately Executed, we ſee <hi>Ireland,</hi> who (as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) took it on his Death, that he was all the latter part of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> hath been proved by ſeveral witneſſes to have been in <hi>London</hi> at the ſame time. And it is notorious, by how vile ſuborna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the reſt have attempted to defend themſelves upon their Trials, which was but one Stage ſhort of their Execution, ſo that they appear to have been men of no very tender conſciences.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe they were, we have no reaſon to believe they would ſtumble at the uſe of Equivocation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parſons</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination. <hi>c.</hi> 12. in the end.</note> For <hi>Parſons</hi> acquaints us that <hi>Equivocations are allowed principally to men of ſcrupulous Conſcience, for avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Lying.</hi> So that upon the whole matter it appears. That they are all a pack of Juglers. Thoſe of them who have little or no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will lie without ſcruple, and thoſe who are of ſcrupulous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will Equivocate without ſcruple, and therefore we may juſtly deſpair of ever learning the Truth from them.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>S. Auguſtinus de Haereſibus cap. Lxx. de Priſcillianiſtis.</bibl>
               <l>Propter occultandas autem contaminationes &amp; turpitudines ſuas habent in ſuis dogmatibus hac verba:</l>
               <l>Jura, perjura, ſecretum prodere noli.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This principle jumps with thoſe of the Jeſuits, and may be thus Engliſhed,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Swear and forſwear you muſt, and not</l>
               <l>Confeſs one tittle of the PLOT.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
